Guide to the Womens’ Recreation Association Papers 1938-1968
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Womens’ Recreation Association Papers
1938-1968
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 302
2.5 linear feet 3 boxes
The collection contains scrapbooks, clippings, papers and photographs concerning the WRA (Womens' Recreation Association) at Washington State University.
The Womens’ Recreation Association (WRA) was set up to fulfill recreational needs and desires of women students on campus. It had three parts: recreational clubs, intramurals, and co-rec. Intramurals gave the women opportunity to compete based on living groups. There was an intramural board which consisted of the vice president of the WRA and two appointed WRA members. The board selected a manager for each activity. The activities included badminton, volleyball, co-ed volleyball, swimming, basketball, bowling, skiing, gymnastics, track and field, archery, synchronized swimming, co-ed golf, tennis, and softball. The Crimson W program also fell under the WRA. The Crimson W, an honorary athletic organization for women, encourages good sportsmanship and sponsors athletic enterprise on the campus. To earn a Crimson W, the women had to participate in a variety of activities within the sports department and earn 900 points.
The collection was maintained in its original order, with the scrapbooks moved to the end. Box 1 consists of the two notebooks and folders with photos and papers relating to meetings, and “Crimson W”. The second box consists of three scrapbook albums which include news clippings and photographs. The third box contains the two scrapbooks added in 2010, removed from their bindings and foldered.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was acquired on December 15, 1992 from Barbara Hagedorn of WSU’s Physical Education, and retained as UA1992-40. It was processed in February 2011 by Library and Information Science graduate student Katrina Burch. During that processing two scrapbooks received in 2009 from Joanne Washburn of WSU’s Women’s Athletics as part of accession UA2009-10 were incorporated into this collection. Processing and description of this collection was funded in part through a National Endowment for the Humanities “We the People” grant for Washington Women’s History to the Washington Women’s History Consortium, a part of the Washington State Historical Society.
Related records relating to dance and the Physical Education Majors (PEM) club can be found in Archives 19.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University--Womens' Recreation Association--Archives; Physical education for women--Washington (State)--Pullman--Archives
Colleges and Universities.; Washington (State)
- Black notebook with Gamma Phi Epsilon written on first page. Contains meeting minutes, 10/13/1938 to 3/18/1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Black notebook with a crimson W on the front cover. Contains installation notice, meeting notes from 10/30/1939 to 5/19/1960, roll call and member lists from 1939-1960, guidelines, and bylaws of the Crimson W organization. 1939-1960 (Folder 2)
- Photographs. Track, undated (Folder 3)
- Photographs. Women’s athletics, archery, undated (Folder 4)
- Blue and gold scrapbook. Includes photos from PE department, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Green/teal scrapbook. All about WRA, including photos, news clips, 1960 (Folder 6)
- PEM (Physical Education Majors) Club scrapbook. Includes photos and news articles. Fragile. 1955 – 1968 (Folder 7)
- WRA Scrapbook, 1942-1955 (Box 3, Folder 8-12)
- WRA Scrapbook, 1956-1967 (Folder 13)
- WRA Scrapbook, 1959 (Folder 14)